Average radius of rotor: |

| mm
cm
inches | Select A Rotor |
Optionally choose another radius parameter:

Relative Centrifugal Force (RCF): |

| × g
Speed (Angular Velocity): |

| revolutions / minute (rpm)
revolutions / second (rps)
radians / second

Press To Update | Select the one result desired if the other two are given: | radius
RCF
speed

| Clear All

Select the units/dimensions first, then enter the value in a box. If a value is first entered in a box, and then the unit/dimension for that value is selected or changed, then the value will automatically be converted. A value entered into a box after units/dimensions are changed will not change the value, of course.

The radius of the rotor is never calculated. A speed for the centrifuge (in revolutions per minute, revolutions per second, or radian per second) is calculated if values for the radius and relative centrifugal force (RCF) are entered, and either one of those has its value changed. An RCF is calculated if values for the radius and speed are entered, and either one of those has its values changed.

In the course of entering a value in a box, use of the TAB or ENTER/RETURN keys or movement of the focus/cursor with the mouse will cause an update operation (calculation), if appropriate, with the value entered to be used in the calculation.

|

The average radius is the distance from the center of rotation to the point in the tube/container where the sample is most likely to be found from the rotational center.

For cylindrical container (tube), the sample at the top of the tube may be closer to the sample at the bottom of the tube. Since the force experienced by the sample depends up the radial distance from the center (radius), if the top of the tube is positioned a shorter distance than the bottom of the tube, sample at the top of the tube (at the minimum radius) experiences less of a force than sample at the bottom of the tube (at the maximum radius). This is especially the case for a swinging-bucket or -carrier type of centrifuge, as the tube swings into its position during the run. For fixed-angle rotors, there is less of a distance between the minimum and maximum radii, and so the force throughout the sample is more uniform.

The practical average radius of a swinging bucket type of rotor where the midpoint of the container's length is the pivot point is the radius to the pivot point. For a fixed-angle rotor, the average radius is the midpoint between the minimum and maximum radius. A little trigonometry solves this problem. If θ represents the angle of the rotor well (tube) from the horizontal toward the center, rmax is the maximal radius of the rotor well, rmin is the minimal radius of the well, and ravg is the average radius (the value desired), then the following equations are true:

(rotor well length) × cos θ = rmax − rmin

Note that ½ × (rotor well length) represents the midpoint of the length of the rotor well, a point that is ravg:

½ × (rotor well length) × cos θ = ravg

ravg can be solved in terms of rmin and rmax:

(rotor well length) × cos θ = 2 × ravg = rmax − rmin
ravg = ½ × (rmax − rmin)

Hence ravg is just the midpoint of the distance between rmin and rmax.

Instructions?

Enter the required values below
More help, please    Show An Example Now click the How is it done? button Now reset/clear the form with the reset button

reset

Check this box if you are practicing these calculations
and want to provide your own answer

Enter here the concentration of the substance in the stock (more concentrated) solution and select the units: | | |

Enter the concentration of the substance in the working (diluted) solution and select the units: | |
Enter the volume of the working (diluted) solution and select the units: | |

FW =

The formula (molecular) weight of the substance is required for this calculation: | g/mol
Enter the answer that you calculated
for the volume of the stock solution to use: | |

How To Use

This calculator determines the volume of a more concentrated stock solution that will be used in preparing a dilute working solution whose desired concentration and volume is known.

This type of calculation is virtually the most commonly done among biological scientists/researchers, and this calculator makes it easy. Calculations of this type apply the law that describes the conservation of mass: the product of solution density (or concentration) and the volume of a solution is equal to the mass of the substance in solution, and since dilution of a more concentrated solution does not change the mass of the solute in solution, then the products of concentration and volume of the solution before and after dilution are equal.

Expressing that as an equation:

C1V1 = C2V2

Example #1: As an example of using this form, suppose one wants to make a 500 ml solution of 0.2 M sodium acetate solution and there is a 3 M sodium acetate stock solution available. Enter "3" in the input box for the stock solution (first box) and select "mol/L" in the dropdown selection list, enter "0.2" in box below for dilute working solution and select its units, and then enter "500" in the box for the volume and select "mL" for the volume dimensions. To get the answer, click the button "How is it done?"

Example #2: Suppose one has a 70% concentrated perchloric acid stock solution and one wants to make 1 liter of a 0.5 M stock solution. (Do not be confused here: "stock" essentially means a solution one will keep stored for regular use. One more dilute stock solution is being prepared from a more concentrated stock, so this calculator is still useful.). Enter "70" top box, "0.5" in the one below, and "1" in the box for the volume. Notice that as the units are selected, that a new entry suddenly appears, asking for a "formula weight" (or molecular weight). Read the formula weight for perchloric acid from the label, and enter it. Note that whenever the concentration units for one solution is ‘a form of grams per unit volume’ and the other is ‘a form of moles per unit volume,’ a formula weight for the substance is required to make the proper conversion.

This calculator also provides a service of letting you calculate the answer yourself and checking it against the computed result. Check the box to activate the part of the form that allows you to enter an answer.

Back to the calculator

Principal Component Analysis (PCA)

Prerequisite Knowledge

A knowledge of parametric statistics will be assumed, such as the fundamental calculation of mean, variance, and standard deviation of normally distributed data. Tests for normality exist to indicate if data is skewed or not.

Covariance and Covariance Matrix

Whereas the variance of a one-dimensional dataset is the sum of square of differences between data about its mean, the covariance is the sum of the product of the difference between two datasets and their mean:

var(x) = { ∑ (xi − x)(xi − x) } / (n − 1)

cov(x, y) = { ∑ (xi − x)(yi − y) } / (n − 1)

for all i from 1 to n. Note that if the computed value is <0, the increase in one dataset involves a decrease in values of the second dataset. If the covariance is 0, then the data are independent of one another.

In a multidimensional dataset, a pairing of each dimension can help in the computation of a covariance. For 3 dimensions, 3 covariance values can be computed. In fact for n dimensions, it is possible to compute n! / (2(n−2)!) covariance values. For all values of all dimensions, a covariance matrix can be constructed with n × n dimensions:

Cn×n = (ci,j, ci,j = cov(Dimi, Dimj).

A three-dimensional x, y, z covariance matrix would look:

C = ( cov(x,x) cov(x,y) cov(x,z) ) cov(y,x) cov(y,y) cov(y,z) cov(z,x) cov(z,y) cov(z,z)

Note that in the matrix, the diagonal is just the variance of one dimension of the dataset. Also the matrix is symmetrical, since cov(a,b) = cov(b,a)

Matrix Algebra

Two matrices can be multiplied together if they meet certain requirements. Suppose a vector is multiplied to a square matrix, which is a transformation matrix. The result is another vector that is transformed from its original position. An eigenvector is a vector that is a multiple of a vector affected by a transformation matrix. Eigenvectors are properties of only certain square matrices: for such n × n matrices, there are n eigenvectors. Eigenvectors as such scale the magnitude of vectors they transform, without altering their direction. An additional property is that all eigenvectors are orthogonal (perpendicular) to the plane of the square matrix. Additionally eigenvectors are scaled to 1 so that they all have the same length.

( 3 ) 2

is an eigenvector with a length of √(3^2 + 2^2) = √13. Thus if the vector is divided by that amount, a vector whose length is one is produced

( 3/√13 ) 2/√13

The eigenvalue is the scaling factor of the matrix to produce the eigenvector.

( 2 3 ) × ( 3 ) = ( 12 ) = 4 × ( 3 ) 2 1 2 8 2

Thus for the matrix, an eigenvector and its eigenvalue are determined.

PCA Defined

[Taken from one single page explanation by NGA Data Mining.]

Reduces dimensionality of large data sets, particularly useful in microarray analysis Finds signals in noisy data

Suppose X is a matrix of data n rows (observations) × p columns (variables), x1, x2, ...,xp. There is another matrix S which is a p × p covariance matrix with the same set of xi variables.

A vector a1 of length p is found such that a1TSa1 is maximized subject to a1Ta1 = 1.

A variable z1 = ∑pi=1 a1i xi represents the first principal component, and provides a linear combination of variables yielding maximum variation. A second principal component, z2 = ∑pi=1 a2i xi is found with the condition that a2TSa2 is maximized subject to a2Ta2 = 0.

A linear combination of variables will now be orthogonal to the first principal component to provide maximum variation. Additional principal components are derived in a similar way.

Vectors a1, a2, ..., ap are eigenvectors of matrix S. Associated with each is an eigenvalue λi^2. The value λi^2 / ∑ λi^2 is the proportion of variation explained by the ith principal component. Alternative, the ai values can be considered to be right singular vectors in a singular value decomposition with singular values λi of the matrix centered about its mean and scaled by 1 / √(n − 1), Xs.

If Xs = V Λ P´, with Λ being a diagonal matrix with elements λi, P´ is a p × p matrix with columns ai, and V is an n × p matrix with V´V = I, this produces the principal component scores.

In reducing the dimensions of data sets, one replaces a large number of correlated variables with smaller number of orthogonal variables containing most of the information of the data set. The choice of the count of dimensions is based on the variation of the leading principal components. If k principal components are selected, the test of equality for the remaining p − k eigenvalues is:

(n − 1 − (2p + 5) / 6 { − ∑p i=k+1 log(λi^2) + (p − k) log ( ∑p i=k+1 λi^2/(p − k) }

This has asymptotically a χ^2 distribution with 1/2(p − k − 1)(p − k + 2) degrees of freedom. Equality in the remaining eigenvalues indicates that if more principal components are to be considered, they should all be considered.

Instead of the variance-covariance matrix, the correlation matrix, sum of squares and cross-products matrix, or a standardized sum of squares and cross-products matrix can be used. In the latter case σ−1/2Sσ−1/2 is used instead of S for a diagonal matrix σ with positive elements. If correlation matrix is used, the χ^2 approximation for the statistic given above is not valid.

Principal component scores F are the values of the principal component variables for the observations. They can be adjusted (standardized) so that the variance of the scores for each component is 1.0 or equal to the corresponding eigenvalue.

In weighting components, the matrix X is first centered about the weighted means, then each row is scaled by an amount √wi where wi is the weight of the ith observation.

pH and pKa: Henderson-Hasselbach

?

pH: | Press To Update

pH
pKa
total concentration

|

pKa: |

Total Concentration: |

|

Theory

Weak acids such as acetic acid (CH3COOH) or phosphoric acid (H3PO4) can be placed in water and reach an equilibrium in aqueous solution in which protons are transferred in the reaction:

HAn + H2O →← An−1 + H3O+

HA represents the protonated (acid) form of A, which is the conjugate base. A has an ionic charge of n while bound to its proton (n could be zero).

The equilibrium constant for this acid-base reaction, also called the acid dissociation constant, is defined as the ratio of the multiplied concentrations of the product and the multiplied concentration of the reactants, as for all equilibrium constants:

Ka = | [An−1] × [H3O+]
[HAn] × [H2O]

By long-standing convention, water is removed from the equilibrium equation because its concentration effectively does not change in dilute acid solutions.

HAn →← An−1 + H+

And the acid dissociation constant is thus defined:

Ka = | [An−1] × [H+]
[HAn]

The following equation takes the logarithm of both sides of the equation above and does some algebraic rearrangement:

−log [H+] = − logKa + log | [An−1]
[HAn]

Note that a principle of logarithms is that log (ab / c) = log a + log b − log c.

By definition, pH = − log [H+], and pKa = − log Ka, and so the following substitutions are made:

pH = pKa + log | [An−1]
[HAn]

This equation is called the Henderson-Hasselbach equation, after the scientists who presented what is really another form of the acid dissociation constant. It essentially states that given the physical property of a weak acid, its acid dissociation constant the Ka, and knowing the ratio of its conjugate base An−1 to its protonated form HAn, one can calculate the pH. Actually one can calculate any parameter of the equation if one knows any of the other parameters.

In many cases the ratio of the conjugate base An−1 and protonated form HAn is not set (and thus not known). For example, if only the acid form or conjugate base (salt of the acid) is placed in solution, then the dissociation must be determined from the total concentration. Assume the total concentration of all forms of the conjugate base A is C (a number representing the solution density, such as 1 M [one molar]). Thus:

C = An−1 + HAn

Now if the acid had been added, the concentration of An−1 and H+ are the same, since acid dissociation means that these ions must be formed equally. And with the dissociation, the concentration of HAn should be the total C less the concentration of An−1 (or H+) that is formed. Assume that x = [An−1] which also equals [H+], and so [HAn] = C − x. The equilibrium equation should now look like this:

Ka = | x^2
C − x

C and Ka are known, and so the solution of x is obtained (use the quadratic equation to solve for the positive root of x). As x represents [H+], the resulting pH of the solution is easily calculated.

Suppose on the other hand, the salt of the acid (conjugate base) is added to water and allowed to reach equilibrium. What is the final pH?

First look at the reaction occurring at equilibrium:

An + H2O →← HAn+1 + OH−

The equilibrium constant, Kb, is:

Kb = | [HAn+1] × [OH−]
[An]

Kb happens to be 10−14 / Ka for the acid form of the conjugate base. As proof of this:

It is well-known that the acid dissociation of water itself

H2O →← H+ + OH−

although the reaction is actually:

2 H2O →← H3O+ + OH−

The acid dissociation constant, Kw, is defined and its value is well known:

Kw = [H+] [OH−] = 10−14

Since [OH−] = 10−14 / [H+], the appropriate substitution is made for the Kb equation:

Kb = | [HAn+1] × 10−14
[An] × [H+]

Since 1 / Ka = [HAn+1] / ([An] + [H+]), then:

Kb = | 10−14
Ka

Now the formation of [HAn+1] and [OH−] in the reaction is equal, and the total concentration of all forms of the acid is C = [HAn+1] + [An]. Substituting correctly, the equation is

Kb = | x^2
C − x

In solving for x, one gets [OH−]. To find the pH, one can calculate the pOH (= −log [OH−]) and then subtract its value from 14, or one can divide 10−14 by the value of [OH−] and then take the negative of the logarithm of the result.

These calculations work well for monoprotic acids and for polyprotic acids whose acid dissociations constants are separated by 3 or 4 orders of magnitude, but can become more complex with polyprotic acids whose acid dissociation constants are within 1-2 orders of magnitude within one another.

For examples, see the How To Use section.

How To Use

The use of this interface is shown by a few examples.

1. A solution of 0.1 M (glacial) acetic acid is prepared. What is the final pH?

One needs to know the acid dissociation constant and the total concentration. This problem is solved using the Ka = x^2 / (C − x) form, and using the quadratic equation to solve for x.

Either enter the pKa or the Ka for acetic acid into the box (or alternatively, select from the list of well known acids or bases, and it will be entered automatically).

Enter the Total Concentration and make sure to select the proper units.

Select the pH to be calculated, and the pH and the concentrations of all the components will be reported.

If the pKa = 4.76, and C = 0.1, then the quadratic equation is used:

x = | −Ka ± √Ka^2 − 4(−Ka × C) | = | −(10−4.76) ± √(10−4.76)^2 − 4(−10−4.76 × 0.1)
2 | 2

The solutions for x are −0.001327 and 0.0013096, but only the positive solution is relevant. Thus [H+] = 0.00131 M, and the pH = −log[0.00131] = 2.88. The concentration of acetate ion [CH3COO−] should be equal to the [H+] concentration, and the concentration of undissociated acid [CH3COOH] will be 0.1 − 0.00131 or 0.09869. Note that the calculation of the pH is independent of knowing the volume of the solution.

2. 10 grams of monobasic sodium phosphate dihydrate (NaH2PO4 • 2 H2O) is mixed with 25 grams of dibasic potassium phosphate (K2HPO4) in a final 500 ml solution. What is the final pH?

The acid is a form of phosphoric acid. Phosphoric acid is a polyprotic acid with three acidic protons with pKa values of 2.3, 7.2, and 12.2. When NaH2PO4 • 2 H2O is dissolved in solution, it produces the ion H2PO4−. When K2HPO4 is dissolved in solution, it produces the ion HPO42−. These two ions are in equilibrium:

H2PO4 →← H+ + HPO42−

Because this is the second proton released from phosphate, the second pKa is relevant to this reaction (pKa = 7.2). The formula weight of NaH2PO4 • 2 H2O is 156. 01 g/mol. The concentration is thus calculated to be (10 g) / (156.01 g/mol × 0.5 L) = 0.1282 M. Note that this is the concentration of all the ions in solution: [Na+] and [H2PO4− ]. The formula weight of K2HPO4 is 174.18 g/mol. The concentration of this molecule in solution is (25 g) / (174.18 g/mol × 0. 5 L) = 0.2871 M. Because there are 2 moles of potassium per mole molecule, its concentration is 0.574 M. However neither the [Na+] or [K+] contribute to the pH calculations, although it does contribute to the ionic strength.

The Henderson-Hasselbach form of the equation can now be used to calculate the pH. Note that [An−1] = 0.2871 M (where n = −1 although that is not significant) and [HAn] = 0.1282 M. Thus pH = 7.2 + log (0.2871)/(0.1282) = 7.55, the final value.

The interface tries to give the user as many options as possible without doing pre-calculations, but some pre-calculations may be necessary.

3. A 50 mM TrisHCl, pH 7.5 solution is to be prepared using Tris base salt and concentrated hydrochloric acid. The final volume is 1 liter. How much Tris base and HCl should be weighed out?

SDS-PAGE Calculations

Fill in the table so that the calculations can be made. The concentrations for stock reagents are typical, but change them to suit your purposes. Click anywhere on this sentence to display detailed instructions.

In volume calculations, add % for pipetting error Make a printable version of this table | Resolving / Separating / Running Gel | Stacking Gel
Final percentage | % | %
Final volume | Volume is specified
Calculate volume from gel dimensions | ml | ml | Count of gels:

resolving height:

cmmm |

stacking height:

cmmm
gel width: cmmm
gel depth: mm
  ml |   ml

| Final Concentration | Volume to Pipet | Final Concentration | Volume to Pipet
M Tris HCl, pH 8.8 | M |   |
M Tris HCl, pH 6.8 | | M |
acrylamide/crosslinker*

30% T / 2.6% C (37.5:1) 30% T / 2.7% C (29.2:0.8) 40% T / 2.6% C (37.5:1) 38.5% T / 2.6% C (37.5:1) 30% T / 3.3% C (29:1) † 20% T / 5% C (19:1)

|   |
% SDS | % |   | % |
ultrapure (Type I, 18 MΩ) water |   |
% ammonium persulfate | % |   |

TEMED |   |

Calculate

Show Example

* crosslinker is typically N,N′-methylene-bis-acrylamide, but may be piperazine diacrylamide (PDA) or N,N′-diallyl-tartardiamide (DATD)
† Note that a 20% T solution is usually only used in DNA-separating gels, not protein-separating gels

Close Help

Instructions

This module is supposed to take the difficulty of remembering the individual components of SDS-PAGE gels (as done by Laemmli) and the volumes necessary for pipetting them. There are basically two gels in this system. A separating (also called resolving or running) gel, in which the proteins are separated, and a stacking gel, in which proteins in solution in the well at the start of electrophoresis are concentrated into a tight band before entering the separating gel. Each gel has its own column both for entry of input values and for display of calculated volumes.

User-required inputs. Wherever a user input is required or allowed, an input textbox is a form control offered to the user. For each gel the user must enter a final percentage. For example, if the user is going to run a 10% gel, then the value 10 should be entered in the Final percentage textbox under Resolving/Separating/Running Gel. Note that a default value of 4% is indicated for the Stacking gel; although this is typical, it can be changed.

The Final volume of gels can either be given by the user directly or computed indirectly from a number of inputs given which include the count of gels and the height, width, and depth of the gel dimensions. Note that when calculating volumes, a pipetting error can be applied to the calculations. Click the checkbox at the top of the table columns where it indicates In volume calculations, add <error value > for pipetting error. A typical value of 15% is a default entry.

There are also five inputs for solution concentration values. Typical values are entered by default but can be changed. The Tris solutions are usually 4× stocks. Note that the final (gel) concentrations of Tris, SDS, ammonium persulfate, and TEMED can not be controlled, since these values are fixed in the method of Laemmli and important for SDS-PAGE. For acrylamide/crosslinker (crosslinker is usually bis-acrylamide) a list of typical acryalmide concentrations is given. Only the total (T) concentration is actually used to calculate the final percentage.

With the exception of the total polyacrylamide concentration, the final concentration of components in the gel is immutable:

Separating gel buffer: 0.375 M TrisHCl, pH 8.8
Stacking gel buffer: 0.125 M TrisHCl, pH 6.8
SDS concentration in both gels: 0.1% SDS
Ammonium persulfate concentration in both gels: 0.05% APS
TEMED concentration: 0.05% in the resolving, 0.1% in the stacking

This is because these values were determined by the work of Laemmli (Nature:London 227: 680, 1970). See below for an explanation of the many variations of the SDS-PAGE system.

Note that the electrode (running) buffer of 25 mM Tris, 192 mM glycine and 0.1% SDS is always made up by dissolving the following in distilled water, and bringing it to a final 1.0 liter volume:

3.0 g Tris (base)
14.4 g glycine
10 ml of 10% SDS or 1 g SDS

There is no need to adjust the pH of the electrode buffer (it will be approximately 8.3).

The acrylamide/crosslinker concentration is expressed usually as a %T / %C, where %T is the total weight per volume of the acrylamide and the crosslinker and the %C is the weight per weight of the crosslinker as a proportion of the acrylamide plus the crosslinker:

%T = | grams acrylamide + grams crosslinker | × 100
total volume (ml)

%C = | grams crosslinker | × 100
grams acrylamide + grams crosslinker

However, the weight per volume of acrylamide and of the crosslinker (bis) is also usually provided: thus a 30% T solution is shown as 29:1, or 29 grams acryamide and 1 gram bis per 100 ml solution. Note that the %C is 3.3 = 1 / (29 + 1).

The final gel percentage, whether it is an 8, 10, or 12% is always an expression of the %T of the solution during polymerization. Thus a 10% gel will be a one-third dilution of a 30% stock, or a one-fourth dilution of a 40% stock, irrespective of the proportion of crosslinker (%C).

U. K. Laemmli used 30% acrylamide (30 g/100 ml) and 0.8% (0.8 g/100 ml) N, N′-bis-methyleneacrylamide, or 37.5 g acrylamide for each 1 g bis (37.5:1) in his original formulation, which has not changed at all. Note that %C = 0.8 g / (30 g + 0.8 g) = 2.6% C. For a 40% T stock solution, the bis is (40 g/100 ml)(0.026) = 1.04 g/100 ml, and the acrylamide is (40.0 g − 1.04 g)/100 ml = 39.0 g/100 ml.

Notes and Variations on SDS-PAGE

Scientists have used a great many variations on the SDS-PAGE system, and there are some important things to note:

If SDS-PAGE is used preparatively, such as for immunoblotting or gel excision to MALDI-MS, it is important to cast the gel a few hours before its use, so that the gel can cure: freshly polymerized gels are thought to have too many free radicals (persulfate) present which can react with proteins. However this has been disputed by some, who say that the free radicals are negatively charged and will move ahead of the proteins.
The final percentage of APS and TEMED in the monomer solution varies a great deal. U. K. Laemmli used 0.025% (w/v) APS and 0.025% (v/v) TEMED in his original widely cited paper. However, Bio-Rad recommends users of its systems
A great many are leaving SDS out of the stacking and separating gels. This allows cast gels to be storable for longer periods, and the idea is that the SDS present in the sample buffer and electrode buffer keeps the proteins exposed continuously to the proper concentration of SDS, and that SDS has a significant mobility and would distribute in the gels anyway.
Commercial pre-cast gels with a stacking and separating gel put pH 8.8 Tris buffer in both gels rather than pH 6.8 Tris in the stacking. The reason is that mixing of the buffers in the different gels occurs rapidly because of diffusion, and stacking occurs anyway if the sample buffer itself is pH 6.8.

Marker # | MW | Rm or Travel
1 | |
2 | |
3 | |
4 | |
5 | |
6 | |
7 | |
8 | |
9 | |
Dye Front: |
Type of fit:
Linear Polynomial | Clear Form
Show Example

Enter the MW of the protein standard you used in the gel. The order of entry does not matter (no need to sort from increasing to decreasing or vice-versa).
Enter either the Rm value or the distance the marker band traveled starting from the top of the gel (the dimensions/units do not matter, so long as you always measure in the same units). If you decide to enter the distance traveled, you must also enter the distance that the dye front traveled in the entry boi>Choose the type line fit you want. A graph will be presented showing the plotted points and line fit. This may be informative.
To determine the MW of an unknown band or spot, enter the Rm or the distance traveled. The Estimated MW should appear below.

Notes:

The Rm, or relative mobility, is the fraction that a protein band or spot travels in SDS-PAGE relative to the dye front. By definition, it must be a value between 0 and 1. For example, suppose in a mini-gel the BSA (66 kDa) marker moves 2.7 cm and the dye front moves 6.2 cm from the start (top) of the resolving gel. The BSA Rm thus is 2.7 cm / 6.2 cm = 0.435. The system is generally smart enough to know the difference between values entered being Rm or distance travelled.
Errors or irregularities will be noted when possible. It is the responsibility of the user to make careful entries since error checking is not rigorous.
The principle of electrophoresis should work for protein and DNA gels. For MW you can enter the bases (base pairs), and the Rm value should be the same.

Enter Unknown Band/Spot Rm or Travel:

Estimated Molecular Weight:

Instructions?

| FW =

Other:

?

Not Recognized Unknown Character
(See Help) No Space Character
(See Help)

|

Enter the desired solution density (concentration) and indicate the dimensions:
| Units:
µG (micrograms)
mG (milligrams)
G (grams)
kG (kilograms)
µmol (micromoles)
mmol (millimoles)
mol (moles) | per | µL (microliter)
mL (milliliter)
L (liter)

|

Enter the final volume of your solution:
| Units:
µL (microliter)
mL (milliliter)
L (liter)

short version | long version
Give me the lowdown

Note Pressing this button opens a new window

Show Examples

Print Please read the following steps to prepare your solution:

Weigh out on a balance accurate to the nearest exactly of
Pour (or weigh) the into either:

a graduated cylinder if you have a PTFE (Teflon)-coated magnetic stirring bar that comfortably fits into and spins in the graduate cylinder and which can mix the entire solution at full volume in the with a reasonably viewable vortex or,
a beaker containing the proper Teflon-coated stir bar.

Before adding the , fill your container with approximately (about 80% of the final volume) with water of the proper quality (see elsewhere for a discussion of proper water quality).
Begin stirring on a magnetic stirrer to dissolve the . For certain salts, dissolution is aided by slight (40-50°C) or even moderate (as much as 80-90°C) heating. Don't be so quick to use heating however since it will be necessary to cool the solution prior to adding the remaining amount of water to the final volume; note the temperature etched on the glass of the vessel container is the temperature at which the solution and solvent must be for the final addition of water to produce the accurate concentration. Another reason to avoid heating is if the chemical is heat-sensitive and destroyed or altered above a certain temperature.
When the substance has dissolved (there may be insoluble impurities present however) to the best of your experience, then q.s. (add water) to the mark representing the final volume. Note that the bottom of of the meniscus at the air-water interface must align with the mark The final concentration of the solution will be accurate if the temperature of the solution is at the temperature marked on the glass of the container, plus or minus 5°C.
If the entire volume of the solution is not used immediately and it is intended that the solution is to be a working stock solution to be stored and used from from time to time, obtain an appropriate container for storage. If the substance is light-sensitive, it is especially important to use a container that reduces or even eliminates the transmission of room light through the container wall into the solution. A dark brown glass container is adequate for most purposes where light sensitivity is a consideration; alternatively, any glass container wrapped well in something like aluminum foil is sufficient. The bottle cap and its seal should be nonreactive with the solution. Be suspicious of using solutions where inspection of the material of the bottle cap seal shows it has disintegrate or been discolored possibly because of contact or the presence of the solution. Use appropriately non-reactive storage vessels with particularly corrosive solutions.

The bottles of all solutions should absolutely be labeled properly. Proper labeling prevents losses and waste that add to the supply costs of the laboratory when improper labeling requires discarding of substances whose contents or concentrations are unknown. There is also a safety factor, since certain chemicals are hazardous and must be discarded in hazardous waste containers (as opposed to dumping into the sink); hazardous waste disposal is very expensive, all the more so when one is using the service to discard a chemical that is harmless and disposed of by less expensive (or cost-free) means. Proper labeling requires printing in block letters large enough to be seen several feet away first the concentration then the name of the substance: A date (in short form) should be written as well. The initials the person preparing the solution may be useful or necessary as well, perhaps in accordance with policy of a multi-member lab or to identify ownership, etc.

Each solution has a certain shelf or storage life when stored in ideal conditions and when volumes are sampled properly. Where information regarding the life and usefulness of solutions is insufficient, experience will fill the void.